hello my name is Daniel 'shmock de
burger and the founder of a research
project called strategic global
solutions that was started in early 2007
primarily aimed at answering the
question if we care about dolphins and
whales in the health of the oceans and
the welfare of people in Africa and
children all around the world and
education and healthcare reform and all
of it
excluding nothing and recognize the
problems in all these areas as
inextricably interconnected and our
deepest desire is to support the
evolution of a global system that
supports and makes possible the highest
quality of life for all life now and
evolving Li how do we get from here to
there as effectively and efficiently and
quickly as possible as one integrated
project factoring everything and that
really appealed to us as a meta
imperative for our species and that for
all evolutionarily minded m:9 inclusive
value humans this is really our goal how
do we organize our activity as a species
towards the evolution of the most
effective viable fulfilling world system
for all and in order to answer that
question how do we get from here to
there as effectively as possible we
recognize that understanding the data
points of here and they are very well
with a first critical starting place and
so when we look at what the data point
of here it is we started to inventory
what are all of the areas of need what
are all the areas of global problems and
this is all the problems in education
and in agriculture and then species
extinction and then fundamental flaws of
economics and governance structures and
all of that to really be able to deeply
inventory what are all the areas that
need resource allocated to them
we find that we have three primary areas
we look at what are the areas of human
and environmental need that are already
being met to some level and we want to
make sure that they continue to be met
at that level or higher as we you know
work with other things
what are existent problems that need
remediated and then the development of
new technologies and systems that can
meet needs at a higher level and we
found that there is no centralized
inventory of what we as a species really
need to do to make life on this planet
viable for everybody that you end
inhabit the organization's did and
they're a bunch of parts of it in
different places and as much as many of
us might have romanticized about if we
had the power to really make changes in
the world what we'd like to do we
realize that if we were in that position
that we were profoundly under-informed
to actually know what needs done in what
timescales how to allocate resource to
all of that with the most effective ways
to go our and then this was clearly
information that we needed to develop in
you know great detail to be able to have
that power and so whereas we're
inventory in problems or what you could
call more generally areas that need
resource allocated to them we saw that
we needed to develop the right kinds of
metrics to be able to compare all these
issues and so we looked at metrics like
what the scope of any particular issue
was how much human life was affected by
this issue directly and indirectly where
we specified what direct and indirect
means how much non-human life is
affected directly and indirectly what
the magnitude of that effect is which
means how much quality of life is
affected we need to look at urgency
which is what are the timescales
in which these issues have to be
addressed that if certain benchmarks
aren't reached within the critical mass
points of irreversible harm occur so
that we so that you know the timelines
in which we have to address these things
how are all the different problems
interconnected so this particular
problem feeds into all these other ones
so we can see that agriculture and soil
issues feed into water table issues for
instance and that these issues are also
fed into by everything from economic
make issues to issues with pesticides
and genetically modified processes and
all these things so for any issue what
are all the areas that feed into it
we're all there is it feed out of it so
that as we're looking at resource
allocation we can start to look at the
complexity of the interaction of how we
address something making sure that it
doesn't externalize harm to other areas
inadvertently and that we've maximized
the externalization of positives to
other areas and that we can see how as
we work on any part of it how that
affects the systemic overall evolution
of the whole which is really our goal
and then we also look at the etiology of
each of these issues how those issues
came into being and what the political
components are and the economic vested
interest components and the
technological components and social
value system components and all the
levels of cause and effect that has to
be addressed for an issue to really be
fundamentally resolved and so when we
address all the levels of cause and
effect and we address all the
interconnection then we really are
looking at fundamentally viable
solutions and one of the reasons we got
into this was because of a background in
many different areas of activism and
seeing how much problems were mostly
just moved because they didn't address
all the levels of cause and effect and
all the interconnections and how much
well intentioned activist I mean that
doesn't have a deep enough understanding
of the problems how they all
interconnect and deep enough strategy
involved to really be truly affected and
we want to make sure that all good
intentioned heartfelt action is backed
by the most intelligent strategy to
really produce the best results with
just you know all of our goal and so all
of these metrics for what we can call
the problems end up serving as a basis
for being able to evaluate most
effective strategies and best practices
which then we also start to inventory
what are all of the solutions to be able
to address each of these problems
whether all the solutions have been
proposed so far and how to be able to
look at the input to output ratios for
all these solutions how much resource it
takes to do a particular solution for
how much measurable change comes out of
it and measurable change in that local
area of concern and then
we'll change globally when we factor how
it intersects everything else and so our
goal then is to be able to have the most
effective strategies in their particular
area and the strategies that have the
most effective overall impact and look
at how strategies in different sectors
inter affect each other symbiotically to
have strategy guilds and so as we're so
we're inventory the problems in
mentoring the strategies also then
inventory what are the physical
resources that we have to work with on
this planet and this is looking at
things like the reusability of waste
streams what we currently call waste
with you know our current and the
developing technologies available as
well as the things traditionally called
resource because we need to know what we
have to work with resource wise what we
have to work with strategy wise which is
what converts resources into meeting
needs and what the needs are and all of
this together informs also an awareness
of what the sustainable carrying
capacity for our planet is which right
now is guessed at at best and the guess
is very hugely from a population much
less than what we currently have to more
than what we currently have this is a
very important thing that we need to
know as we move forward and obviously
that the carrying capacity is not a
fixed number but is a range that's based
on how efficient the technologies are
for for moving resources into meant
needs how high a quality of life is
being met and you know as several
factors and so this is all part of the
project at work
so the next data point is getting clear
on the there which is where are we going
where do we want to be going and in
activism and in governance so far
oftentimes we are moving away from
problems we're in reaction to but
without a very clear awareness of what a
truly functional model would look like
and so we started asking questions like
if we were going to redesign human
society and human civilization from the
ground up today without assuming that
any of the ways that we have done things
so far necessarily the best ways to
proceed
they might possibly be but really being
able to inventory the starting with the
best of everything we know of of Science
and Technology and all like that today
what the best ways of meaning human
needs in conjunction with the
environment harmoniously would be how
would we do how do we design
civilization what would education look
like well the transportation look like
if we weren't trying to retrofit maybe a
fundamentally flawed system but we're
designing it starting with starting from
scratch starting with the best of
everything that we know now and with the
modularity and evolve ability to be able
to evolve as quickly as possible with
the input of new better strategies and
so that we could really develop a
blueprint and of course an ever evolving
blueprint that gets to synthesize the
best of information from all sources of
where we are wanting to move and so our
approach has looked like like this with
regard to governance models for instance
and governance in the most general sense
means how we collectively make decisions
about what it is that we need to do and
how to best go about doing it and
governance in general is different than
government which is a particular
structure of how we do it the biggest
overall subjects that we're looking at
here is a new structure of how we
collectively make decisions about what
we need to do and how we best to do it
which is a new system of governance it
is
Sara Lee global because of fundamentally
almost all of our issues pollution and
war and trade and all like this are
global issues and a new system of
economics that in its deepest sense
means a basis for how we allocate
planetary resources towards which value
system are we allocating them to
maximize differential advantage of a few
over many or are we working to allocate
them in a manner that scientifically
optimizes the possibility for quality of
life for all life and so with regard to
governance systems we we start by
looking at all the governance systems
that have been attempted so far in a
really philosophically uninvested in
scientifically critical way to look at
what the effective and the uneffective
parts of each of these have been what
are the really effective parts of
capitalism that involve things like
maximizing you know motive to the
individual and then what are the
dysfunctional parts of it which is some
of the pathological kinds of competition
and ex externalization of harm and like
that that occurs and what are the you
know what are the functional parts of of
communism in those systems that were
recognizing that people are affected by
the whole and we need to make sure that
we're taking care of the whole and then
what were some of the dysfunctional
parts like having individual human
motive not be maximized by those systems
and how can we work to take the
functional parts of all the systems that
we've tried so far based on a good
analysis of the metrics that are
involved divested of the dysfunctional
parts and synthesize the functional
parts of everything that humanity has
learned so far to a best of what we know
on this topic for instance governance
and then also to look at what we know
about regulatory systems and control
systems from other systems like
cybernetics and computer science and
regulation of information flow systems
and when we look at nature and we look
at how an ecosystem governs which is
more of a kind of a bottom-up emergent
governance
top-down imposed governance but where
there's so many moving parts that have a
immaculate kind of balance what are the
what's the operating system what are the
governance principles that are there and
them so we have kind of a biomimicry for
social design and all of this is
speaking to how to apply the scientific
method and all the methodologies of
science which is an opinion divested
fact-based decision making system to
social design and to societal design and
this is what Carl Sagan and Buckminster
Fuller and Jacque fresco and many have
talked about as being fundamentally
necessary for a long time there's not
really a Republican versus a Democrat or
a capitalist versus a communist way of
cleaning dirty water or bringing water
to people that need it there's more and
less effective ways of doing that in
terms of input of resource to output of
what are you you know desired output is
and so how do we have a governance
system that is as opinion divested as
possible as fact-based as possible as
aamna inclusive in the goal of what it
is that we're working on as possible and
and so this is you know really what
we're looking at and obviously then the
question is what really is the goal what
do we call quality of life and this is a
very deep topic that we also look at
when we're talking about maximizing the
possibility for quality of life for all
life what are the metrics that we're
looking to optimize because we know that
GDP is not a good metric and then GDP
per capita is not a good metric if we're
really looking at you know individual
happiness and an interpersonal happiness
and sustainability with the planet and
so the goal is to be able to look at all
of the different possible relevant
metrics how they intersect each other
and bring them into an integral picture
that's able to factor all of that and
continuously factor new variables and
metrics
so it's an elastically updatable system
to give us the most comprehensive basis
of what we're seeking to optimize so we
want to look at when we're looking at
maximizing quality of life we want to
look at subjective metrics people's
reporting of their own happiness
all the different dimensions of life
which is their their happiness in their
sense of creativity and contribution and
personal relationships and all like that
and we also want to look at objective
metrics which is we look at things like
suicide rate and mental illness rate and
crime rate and all the different things
that that look at both how functional
the system is from the point of view of
individuals from the point of view of
how individuals interact from the point
of view of how whole societies and
communities interact with each other and
how they interact with the ecosystem and
sustainability and then we also look at
factors involving time do we want people
that are happy now and not really
motivated to evolve over people that are
involving motivated by discontent and
obviously we care about both happiness
now and evolution into ever higher
possibilities of happiness and the
expression of human potential so how do
we maximize both of these simultaneously
and how do we answer all of this in a
collective way that pulls the best of
everything that we know that's
empirically founded that's opinion
divested and where we and what we don't
know for sure how do we set up social
experiments to really be able to
determine these things as best as
possible and feed back and forth that
ground-up social experiments to a
centralized database of knowledge
regarding these topics so critical path
analysis is looking at how we get from
here to there for any particular here
and there factoring many variables in a
complex system and we look at which
things can happen simultaneously
independent of each other which things
have to happen subsequently because they
depend upon the results of previous set
of action and how do how do we allocate
the total amount of resources we have to
each area in light of how that maximizes
the systemic movement and what are the
best practices and best strategies for
the utilization of that resource in each
area and all this comes together to do
critical path now when we're looking at
the critical path for humanity's success
it's a dynamic critical path because the
here points is continuously changing
as our global problems and global needs
change and this can happen in
unpredicted ways all the time and a new
earthquake occurs and now we need to be
able to look at those resource needs
allocated it's dealing with that and
that means resources being taken from
somewhere else and yet we still have all
of our comprehensive goals how do we
really optimize that process so we have
a continuously changing here point and
it continues changing their point as new
technologies emerge in new social
understandings emerged to where what the
best of what's possible for societal
design this keeps changing and so how do
we elastically upgrade and update our
critical path with the input of all new
relevant information to where we know
what we need to be doing now that is
most effective towards the most
long-range goals and all of our timely
goals and that what we're doing now is
continuously optimized in light of the
input of all new real information and so
this requires a lot of complexity
factoring and so this is another thing
that we've looked at which is how do we
see how a particular problem relates to
problems in other areas and potentially
unintuitive a as when we only take a
specialist approach and how does a
particular solution there end up
affecting other areas because we can see
sometimes in solving a particular
problem in particular way we can
actually externalize harm to another
area unanticipated ly like for instance
when we were working to get off of
foreign oil by creating biofuels but in
the process creating biofuels from
agricultural sources that created
environmental damage we want we want to
be able to make sure that as we're
solving a particular problem we're not
externalizing that harm somewhere else
so this requires a cross-sectoral
analysis and have a functional
cross-sectoral analysis we make sure
that we're looking at all the other
sectors appropriately we need to know
what all the sectors are this requires a
taxonomy of all of the issues that we're
looking at and how they all interrelate
to each other and then how our our goal
is to be able to have solutions that are
both optimized for their particular area
of
and optimized for the systemic benefit
when we factor all of the externalized
positives and negatives and this overall
factoring all of our current problems
and areas of need and the timelines and
the interconnections and the scope and
the magnitude on all of that factoring
all the resources we have to work with
factoring all the potential strategies
in the way of synthesizing those
strategies and how the strategies in
turn affect each other and looking at
where we're wanting to go and what about
that we know and is clear what about
that is not yet clear that means
refinement and experimentation to really
be able to know where we want to go in
light of the most comprehensive kinds of
metrics of what quality of life really
means and being able to optimize how we
get from here to there continuously
recognizing there's no fix there point
it's a continuously evolving progressive
there this whole process of how we
collectively make decisions and how we
cook and how we collectively allocate
resource in a scientifically optimized
way creates the basis for planetary
operating system in a new system of
global governance and economics which is
how do we as a conscious species
recognizing that we're profoundly
interconnected that all of our needs
that all of our problems that all of our
welfare is profoundly interconnected not
just with other humans in our area but
with all other humans and with all other
species and not just now but ongoingly
recognizing that how do we organize all
of our efforts and intentions and
endeavors in specific areas in light of
a whole meta endeavor in an optimized
way and this really is what appeals to
us is not a another project amongst the
many projects but an organizational
system that can potentiate and maximize
the efficiency of and the interconnected
strategy between all projects all
positive endeavors that need to be
happening and that's ultimately what our
goal is here is a meta system
for global governance and organization
of all evolutionary human activity in
the broadest sense the direction of
evolution is ordering complexity higher
orders of complexity which is two things
it's more parts that are involved more
complexity and ordering that if we get a
more complex system without adequate
order we end up just getting more
entropy and into grades to the last
level and so if we look at a cell a cell
has all of the complexity of the
component molecules that make it up but
they're arranged in a particular way
that if we just had all of the molecules
that make up a cell thrown in a petri
dish it wouldn't be a cellular just be a
heap of molecules it wouldn't be that
interesting when you arrange it when you
order it that togetherness is what
allows the cell to respirate and to
replicate even though none of the parts
on their own do that and those emergent
properties come from ordering the parts
into a whole and you know we can look at
the same way in terms of a nervous
system and no neuron by itself thinks or
feels it has a particular fire encoder
but when you order the firing pattern of
all those neurons together in the way
that the human brain and nervous system
works you get sentience and you get
eyeness and consciousness well in the
same way we have as all of the many
neurons are connected in our brain to
create human consciousness and all of
the cells are connected in a particular
pattern to create a human organism we
have all of these cells of human beings
on this planet that when they're not
ordered is basically just like a whole
bunch of cells separately which is not
that interesting but when their
activities are ordered together in light
of a higher order than humanity as an as
an organism of sorts actually gets to
emerge and there are emergent properties
that get to arise from that and what
we're looking at creating here with this
global operating system is kind of a
network for being able to take the
database inside
Shuman and be able to to take what
everybody knows to be able to vet it and
synthesize it into a collected database
that is ever-evolving of the best of
what humanity knows about everything so
far that is both able to be fed into by
all people and fed out the relevant
parts to all people for maximizing our
collective engagement organization and
activity and so rather than just being a
bunch of separate neurons there's
actually a nervous system and a
consciousness rather than just being a
bunch of separate human individuals
there's actually humanity as not just a
concept but really a functional entity